A Guide to the Papers of George R. Minor, 1929-1994
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library
Papers of George R. Minor 1929-1994
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, University of Virginia
MS-51
1 box, 5"x10.5"x15.5," .5 feet, 20 folders
Historical Collections
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated by the Department of Surgery.
Biographical/Historical Information
Dr. George R. Minor was born in Cannel City, Kentucky, on October 18, 1913. He attended high school at the Hazel Green Academy of Kentucky and his first two years of college at the University of Arizona. He transferred to the University of Virginia and was awarded a B.S. in Chemistry in 1936 and his M.D. four years later. He contracted tuberculosis while a student at the University of Virginia and was sent to Blue Ridge Sanitarium as an extern and to recuperate. After graduation he served as a staff physician at the Blue Ridge Sanitarium for two years, and his interest shifted from Internal Medicine to Surgery, especially to the then new field of Thoracic Surgery. From 1942 to 1944 he was an intern on the Surgical Service at UVa and then spent four years at the University of Michigan Hospital where he did a year of residency on Thoracic Surgery, became an Instructor in Thoracic Surgery and then Instructor in General Surgery. He was under the tutelage of Dr. John Alexander, a pioneer in the field of Thoracic Surgery. While at Michigan Dr. Minor again developed tuberculosis and spent six months in bed. After he recovered he briefly became an assistant Professor of Surgery at the University of Illinois. From there he returned in 1949 to the University of Virginia as an Assistant Professor of Thoracic Surgery where he and E. Cato Drash, chief of Thoracic Surgery, comprised the whole division.
Dr. Minor did the first mitral valve surgery at UVa in 1953 and was also the first to perform the division of the patent ductus arteriosus, and repair of coarctation of the aorta between 1950 and 1954. He did the first 200 cardiac catheterizations with Dr. John Guerrant who assisted with pulmonary functions. He established the Endoscopy Suite at UVa. In 1964 he became Professor of Thoracic Surgery and Assistant Dean of the Medical School.
Dr. Minor traveled widely during his life, with many two- to five- week trips abroad during the summer. He was seriously injured in an auto accident in Romania in 1970. He was flown back to UVa for surgery and treatment and recuperated in the hospital for six months. In 1972 he entered the faculty exchange program and was an Exchange Professor of Surgery for two years in Tunisia. He was then a consultant in Taiwan at Chang Gung Memorial Hospital, a facility that had 40 operating rooms at the time.
Dr. Minor was a member of the American College of Surgeons, the Society of University Surgeons, the American Thoracic Society, and the Virginia Surgical Society. After his retirement in 1984 his many students and colleagues established the Chair of Thoracic Surgery in his name. He continued to see a small number of patients after retirement. He also maintained his interest in gourmet cooking, (enhanced by his own garden), fluency in multiple languages, and playing classical piano music on his Steinway.
Dr. Minor died at his residence in Charlottesville on November 29, 2007, at the age of 94.
Scope and Content
The collection contains mostly talks and lectures given by Dr. Minor. The talks mainly focus on diseases affecting the chest or thorax such as asbestos related diseases, pericarditis, empyema, gastroesophageal reflux, lung abscesses and lung cancer, and solitary pulmonary lesion. Dr. Minor's interest in history is illustrated by his talks in Renaissance medicine, the early days of thoracic surgery, and biographies of great thoracic surgeons.
Arrangement
The folders are arranged alphabetically by subject.
Contents List
- Academic life April 1929 (Box-folder 001-001)
  Reprint of "A Note on the Academic Life" by Edwin P. Lehman, first published in the Archives of Surgery.
- "Asbestos Related Diseases" after 1980 (Box-folder 001-002)
  a talk with slides
- Constrictive Pericarditis 22 June 1968, 1980 (Box-folder 001-003)
  Constrictive Pericarditis lecture outline for Surgical Grand Rounds, 22 June 1968 and lecture outlines for 3rd year surgery.
- "Empyema" and "Empyema thoracis" after 1973 and after 1980 (Box-folder 001-004)
  Thoracic surgery lectures
- Fungus Infections n.d. (Box-folder 001-005)
  Lectures
- "Gastroesophageal Reflux (G-E-R) and Reflux Disease (Peptic Esophagitis)" 1986-1987 (Box-folder 001-006)
- "Lung Abscess" after 1978 (Box-folder 001-007)
  Thoracic surgery lecture
- Lung Cancer 28 February 1983 (Box-folder 001-008)
  Surgical Grand Rounds
- Lung Cancer 26 April 1984 (Box-folder 001-009)
  Bibliography
- "Lung Cancer" 12 October 1984 (Box-folder 001-010)
  The Fourth Byrd Leavell Symposium
- "Lung Cancer: A Perspective of 40 Years" 21 January 1985 (Box-folder 001-011)
  Talk given in honor of radiologist John Kroll.
- Lung Cancer 1990 (Box-folder 001-012)
  "A New Look at Lung Cancer"
- Minor genealogy n.d. (Box-folder 001-013)
  Includes Minors who were born as early as 1640 and as late as 1843.
- Miscellaneous notes n.d. (Box-folder 001-014)
- "The Pleura" n.d. (Box-folder 001-015)
- Renaissance medicine 1987 (Box-folder 001-016)
  "Medicine during the Renaissance," a talk with slides given in the Arts and Sciences Revisited course at Northern Virginia Regional Center
- "The Solitary Pulmonary Lesion" by George R. Minor 13 December 1961 (Box-folder 001-017)
  Talk given at the Peninsula Academy of Medicine, Newport News, Virginia
- Thoracic Surgery: "The Early Days of Thoracic Surgery" 18 April 1978 (Box-folder 001-018)
  Talk given by George R. Minor for the University of Virginia Medical History Society.
- Thoracic surgeons after 1977 (Box-folder 001-019)
  Biographies with notes of great thoracic surgeons
- Tuberculosis 1994 (?) (Box-folder 001-020)
  Thoracic Surgery lecture: "The New Tuberculosis"